I mean, I wasn't just pissing off NSA, I
was pissing off the Russians.
>> This is Martin Hellman, a Turing Award
winner famous for his contributions to
public key cryptography that the
government was against.
>> I told them, "Look, if you want to give
the papers, that's okay, but Stanford's
not sure they can defend you or us, it's
clear they could defend me. I could have
gotten killed."
So, when my colleagues said [music] I
was crazy to work in cryptography,
instead of scaring me off, it actually
attracted me.
>> The NSA, did they ever try to recruit
you?
>> When I looked at it, I went, "Oh, shit."
Basically, uh
>> I saw your initial work in cryptography
was potentially breaking laws, or was
kind of in this gray area where the NSA
was kind of, you know, not super happy
with your work, and there was some, you
know, conflict with the government.
Could you explain what the field of
cryptography was like at the time and
its relationship to the the government
and how you got into the field?
>> Cryptography is the study of codes and
ciphers, keeping information secret. Uh
when I started to get interested in this
area in the uh let's see, it was 1960
uh eight at I was at IBM Research uh
just after finishing my PhD.
Uh they'd hired Horst Feistel, who you
may have heard of, who was the father of
IBM's work in this area, and really
started the uh
uh unclassified research in
cryptography. So, I started there, and I
then I realized when I was teaching at
MIT '69 to '71 that I might actually be
able to do something. I won't go into
the the details of that right now. Uh
and I did it in my own time cuz I didn't
think I was breaking any laws by doing
it. I didn't think anybody could make
that case, but I realized that there was
a part of the government, the National
Security Agency, that would be very
concerned about this.
And then it was as our work really
became uh
uh
visible that they started saying we were
breaking the laws. And that's when I
looked into it more carefully. Uh, we
got a letter in July 1977,
uh,
from, uh,
uh, a guy who worked at We determined he
worked at NSA. He wrote from his home
address in Maryland, which is a good
indicator that he works at NSA, to the
IEEE, which is the main electrical
engineering professional society, the
Institute of Electrical and Electronics
Engineers, uh, saying that as an IEEE
member he was concerned that they were
breaking the law by publishing certain
papers. He never mentioned me by name,
but he I had an article in every almost
every issue that he mentioned of the
IEEE transactions.
Uh, and the IEEE wrote back to him,
copying me. They didn't copy me as
Martin Hellman troublemaker, they copied
me as a member of the Board of Governors
of the Information Theory Group, which
was then publishing most of these
papers. Uh, and, uh, so it's a funny
thing that when people start to talk
about cryptography, they talk in code
all the time. NSA was maintaining I was
breaking the law by publishing my papers
in international journals.
The ITAR, the International Traffic in
Arms Regulations, which I'd been unaware
of up to that point, uh,
defines anything cryptographic as an
implement of war. And I wasn't exporting
an implement of war, which which you
need a a, um, license from the State
Department. I was exporting technical
data from that perspective on implements
of war. And so that's why I was breaking
the law. And so I took the letter to,
um, Stanford's General Counsel, uh, at
the time, John Schwartz. He said,
"If the law is interpreted that broadly,
he thinks it was unconstitutional, but
that's only his legal opinion. It had to
be settled in a court of law."
>> I mean, when you got these warnings,
did it did it deter you at all? Or what
was your immediate reaction?
>> I kind of fell into this. At first, Whit
and I, Whit Diffie, and I thought that
um the 56-bit key size of DES, the data
encryption standard, was a mistake. You
know, and we realized that you could
break it with with um exhaustive search.
Uh today, the AES, the advanced
encryption standard, has a minimum of a
128-bit key size, which is much, much
bigger than a 56-bit key size.
Uh 2 to the 128th is much bigger than 2
to the 56. Uh so, we we we wrote
letters. We thought that they'd change
it. It was cheap and easy to change it.
And after 6 months, we realized that we
had a political problem, not a technical
problem. And then, we had to decide
whether to back down or not. And we went
forward because at that point, I was
invested in this. And also, I'm from the
Bronx, as I mentioned to you earlier.
And uh I'm a street fighter, not with my
fists. I got beat up a lot.
But I'm a street fighter with my mouth
and my mind. And uh they they picked the
wrong person, basically. Uh I wasn't
going to back down.
>> Well, what could have gone wrong? I
mean, would they pursue you with lawyers
or would
>> Oh, I I could have gotten killed.
>> You could have gotten killed.
>> Oh, yeah. Not not maybe not not
necessarily by them, but maybe by the
GRU, the Russian equivalent. I mean, I
wasn't just pissing off NSA. I was
pissing off the the Russians, the
Soviets.
>> Why would they be pissed off?
>> Oh.
We and the Soviets sold our World War
surplus equip- uh cryptographic
equipment to third-world countries.
We'd rather that they were able to break
it, and they'd rather that we were able
to break it, than no one was able to
break it. So, uh it it My mother called
me up. My mother was still alive. She
died in 1984. And uh she called me up
and said, "What are you doing? You're
going to get yourself killed." She was
really upset.
>> So, okay. So, they you you get issued
the warning, and then you go to the
general counsel at Stanford. The then
what happens?
>> This was July 1977.
Uh Uh, in I think October, early
October, yes, it was October, there was
an IEEE Symposium on Information Theory
at Cornell University. And I had two
papers there, one with Ralph Merkle who
deserves, I believe, a lot of credit for
inventing public key cryptography, as
you probably know. Uh, and one with
Steve which really, uh, Steve
and I have a paper, uh,
which is really the RSA system, except
it's mod P instead of mod N. It's modulo
a prime number instead of modulo a
composite number. We realized that you
could get
you could do it mod N, but we didn't
have public key cryptography then.
Anyway, uh, Steve and I and Ralph and I
had papers, uh, and, uh, John Schwartz
said that, uh, he strongly recommended
that I give the papers instead of the
students. I was going to have the
students give the papers. And so I went
to the students, I told them, "Look, if
you want to give the papers, that's
okay, but Stanford's not sure they can
defend you, whereas it's clear they
could defend me. And I feel very
comfortable going forward with
Stanford's, uh, financial resources."
And the students initially bravely said
that they would give the papers.
After a week, they came back to me.
Their mothers were beating on them
like my mother beat on me, and, uh,
they said, "Okay, you give the paper."
So, when it came time for each of those
papers to be given at Cornell, I went up
to the podium and I said,
I had the student come up with me, and I
said, "Normally, the student would be
giving this paper, but on the advice of
counsel, and everyone knew what I was
talking about, uh,
I will be giving the paper. And I want
you to consider in every way, but
legally, the words coming from my mouth
as if they're coming from his." And so
the students got more credit that way
than they ever would have if they gave
the papers by themselves.
>> It sounds like you had a lot of
opposition at the time. Why did you
still pursue it?
>> Well, what my colleagues all told me
that I was crazy to work in
cryptography, and they had two reasons,
one of which was NSA has a multi-
billion-dollar-a-year budget, and
they've got a decades head start. How
can you hope to discover something they
don't already know?
And my attitude was, I don't care what
they know. It's not available for
commercial use. I need to even if I only
develop things that they know,
it doesn't matter.
And yet we we developed things that they
didn't know about, which is a whole
'nother thing. Like GCHQ, the British
equivalent of NSA, has claimed that they
invented public key cryptography a
little bit before us, not a lot by the
way, just around the same time.
Except they never had anything on
digital signatures. They never had
anything that allowed my phone to accept
a software update and to use a secret
key to sign it, which Apple has, and a
public key in the phone. So even if
someone takes the phone apart and just
the public key, that doesn't tell them
how to sign future software updates. And
GCHQ had nothing on on digital
signatures, only on the privacy aspect.
>> Prior to the solutions you came up with,
how did people how did people
um
you know
>> encrypt it
>> encrypt yeah encrypt messages.
>> They didn't. No, actually NSA, GCHQ,
GRU, all these foreign
United States and foreign intelligence
services were sucking up huge amounts of
unencrypted data. It was only mining
companies and banks that used encryption
and they used very bad encryption.
>> What about like during wars and stuff,
sending messages that they didn't want
other you know
uh
adversaries to be able to read?
>> You talking about military use?
>> Yeah, yeah, exactly.
>> Well, that that's that's that was where
the major use had been
was in the military. And one of the
things I have a talk
on the evolution of public key
cryptography and I start off by saying
I love that people call it
revolutionary. Don't stop saying that.
But by the end of this talk you'll
wonder why it took us so long rather
than why how we ever found it. And they
were almost like big arrows pointing go
here, go here, go here. And one of them
was
Whit and I had come up with the idea of
a
trapdoor cipher.
That was a cipher that was impossible to
break unless you knew trapdoor
information that went into its design.
We've never been able to develop such a
cipher, but we realized that was a
possibility.
And that would be a general's dream
because he could use it if he knew the
trapdoor information, he could use it
securely against his adversary in the
war, but his adversary if they captured
it couldn't use it securely because he
knew the trapdoor information and could
break it. And from there to public key
cryptography is a minor step.
>> I know there's this famous, I think it's
called the Enigma machine and Turing was
involved in that. That's some sort of
encryption mechanism.
>> a gear Basically, it's a World War II
it's the main German field cipher of
World War II the Enigma machine.
It was gear-based and
encryption is a special purpose form of
computation. And computation's gotten a
hell of a lot better. We we do
I don't know.
I'm 80 years old, so that's 16 periods
of 5 years. We can do about
maybe 10 to the 14th. It's not quite 10
to the 16th times as much computation
for a dollar today as we could when I
was born at the end of World War II. I
was born October '45. So Enigma, what
was the primary computing device of
World War II?
Gear-based adding machines. What was the
primary encryption device? Gear-based
encryption machines. Today, we can
do not only computation much better, we
can do encryption much better. In that
case, it it it did it substituted you
the the electricity you you pressed a
letter on a keyboard, it generated an
electrical signal that went through a
sequence of rotors as they're called
which transformed it into another letter
that lit up. And so, you'd set up the
key, which was with the which rotors to
use and what order to put them in and
some other things, and then you'd you'd
type out the message on the keyboard,
and you'd read off the enciphered
message on the lights.
And Alan Turing, who you pointed out in
The Imitation Game, which was the major
movie of like 5 years ago, Alan Turing
figured out how to build
a primitive form of computer to break
the Enigma machine. Now, the Germans
knew Enigma was breakable. They never
thought that the Allies would build a
computer to break it, and so the Allies
were reading German encrypted messages
almost as fast, maybe faster, than the
Germans were.
And that's what was different. And as
they knew Enigma was breakable, they
they
never realized that they never thought
that we would build a machine like that.
And it's interesting, Alan Turing was
hounded to death in the 1950s in spite
of his wartime activities, and this is
covered in the Imitation Game in that
movie. He was hounded to death because
of his homosexual
tendencies,
or more than tendencies. I mean, he was
homosexual. Today, we wonder how
um our parents, grandparents could have
been so uncivilized as to do things like
that.
>> You mentioned in that talk of the the
history of public key cryptography,
there's these everything is pointing
towards these directions. What did you
mean by that?
>> Well, I mean, the uh
uh trapdoor cipher was pointing us
toward public key cryptography. And yet,
a trapdoor cipher makes perfect sense,
cuz almost everything in cryptography
involves trapdoors.
Uh people usually think of public key
cryptography as a trapdoor cryptographic
system, but even a cryptographic system
is a trapdoor, and this is fundamentally
related to a question called P equals NP
or not in computer science.
Are there any problems that are easily
checked that are hard to solve? That's
basically what that means. And if
there's any if there are any secure
cryptographic systems, then
then there are
problems that are easily checked that
are hard to solve.
And so, for example, uh one-way function
is the simplest form of um trapdoor.
This is a function that's easy to
compute but hard to invert. And this
figures importantly in cryptograpy and
blockchains, among other things. Um
and um
so, we've all taken trapdoor
um
uh quiz quizzes where the professor
gives you an hour to solve the problem.
At the end of the hour, he says,
"Pencils down, papers in." And he says,
"Oh, we have a few minutes remaining.
Let me give you the solution and
convince you it's right."
That's a trapdoor quiz problem. It's a
primitive form. And there, the professor
has in mind a particular method for
solving it, whereas you have many
methods.
And a real trapdoor quiz problem would
work work like as follows.
The professor would would say, "Here's a
one-way function.
I've generated an X. Here's the Y that
comes out. You find the X that comes
in." After a million years goes by, he
says, "Papers down, pencils in." And he
says, "Oh, by the way, in the few
seconds remaining, let me convince you
let me give you the solution and
convince you it's right." What does he
do? He takes X, he puts it through the
one-way function, he gets Y, and you
know that he had the right value of X.
And yet, you can never find it.
>> When I imagine you kind of competing or
butting heads with the NSA, I can
imagine one solution for them might be
to try to recruit you to their side. Did
they ever try to recruit you?
>> Yes.
Uh early on, before we had public before
we had any good results, I'd go to
conferences and I'd give talks on
cryptography, which in hindsight were
very primitive. And NSA people with name
badges that said Department of Defense,
which was the uh simple substitution
cipher for NSA. They would always ask me
they they explained they came they were
at NSA and they'd love to hire me as a
consultant cuz they needed new blood.
And I said I'd love to know what you
know, but only if I can't oh, if I can
publish my papers independently. And
they said, "Of course not." And so that
which I knew was the answer. And so I
never took any classified uh consulting
contracts, etc.
Until 1995
there was a National Research Council
committee uh called crisis that it's
called the crisis report cryptography's
role in securing the information society
that which comes out as crisis.
And that was about 1995.
And um
the question was were US government
regulations helping national security or
hurting national security? We concluded
that many ways they were hurting
national security. And we had a former
deputy director of NSA on the committee.
We had a former attorney general on the
committee, Benjamin Civiletti uh who had
been attorney general under Jimmy
Carter. We had people like me who were
privacy advocates, but who had come
around and started to understand how NSA
viewed things. We had uh Ray Ozzie was
on that committee who was the chief
software architect at um
uh Microsoft when Bill Gates retired. Uh
he he did Lotus Notes. Uh and we reached
unanimous conclusions. And one of the
most important conclusions we reached
was that the classified briefings I did
take when I did take a classified I
didn't get paid for that, but I did have
a uh
uh security clearance for that and an
intel- intelligence clearance which I
never taken before.
Uh but I was I was retiring at that
point and I figured it didn't matter.
And it was important for me to
be able to say get past the people who
said, "If you knew what I knew, you'd
think differently."
And there were people in the
unclassified briefings who said if you
knew what we knew you'd think
differently. But we concluded and it's
in our report which you can get free of
charge on the National Academy National
Academy's website.
We had in there that the classified
briefings helped fill in details, but
they did not change our fundamental
conclusions. And that was one of the
most important conclusions we reached.
And yet people said if you knew what we
knew you'd think differently and yet
that was not true.
>> When they were trying to recruit you, I
imagine
it would have been very advantageous for
them to classify your your work. So
the I mean when you turned down their
offer,
I imagine they would have had to
compensate you handsomely to kind of go
to the you know,
outside world.
>> we never got that far.
And by the time we had a fight on our
hands,
it was it was too late. I mean,
basically I'd committed to see this
thing through and when I realized that
my life might be in danger, I might go
to jail, although I didn't think
I I didn't think about those
possibilities very much.
And I didn't think they were real,
although they may have been.
Um
I I felt like I was committed and I
I couldn't back down. I mean, what would
you do? I kind of fell into it. It's
like a friend of mine who was a
helicopter pilot in Iraq.
He was went through ROTC in the late
90s. He said to get his education. He
knew there were no wars. He said, "Why
is everybody calling me hero?"
>> [laughter]
>> When I was doing the research, I kept
seeing this mention of
first crypto wars. What are the the
crypto wars that and how did they play
out?
>> The first crypto war was the one we've
we've been talking about which occurred
in the late 70s early 80s where NSA
threatened to throw me in jail.
My life may have been in danger things
like that.
And that was over two things. It was
over the freedom to publish papers
in international journals, which is now
been established, and it was over the
key size of DES, which is something that
people today know almost nothing about.
As I mentioned before, it was a 56-bit
key size, and Whit and I did a quick
calculation that you could probably
break that for $10,000 even with 1976
technology, 1975 technology.
And if we were wrong, Moore's law would
have if we were off by a fact by a
factor of 10, an order of magnitude,
that would be erased in 5 years' time
because Moore's law was advancing the
state of computing by an order of
magnitude every 5 years in those days.
So, that was the first crypto war. It
was over the freedom to publish and the
the key size of DES.
The second crypto war,
which people don't really remember, was
in the '90s, and Clipper Chip was a big
piece of that. This was the idea that
there should be an escrow service that
the government would allow strong
encryption, but it would maintain master
keys somewhere.
And
if they got a court order that said that
they were able to get into something,
they'd be able to do it.
Well, this sounds great.
And it was great from certain points of
view, but there were problems with it.
Like in the National Research Council
Committee, the crisis committee that I
talked about, we wasted a lot of time
talking about key escrow.
And then we realized
I may have actually said this, although
I think we came to it as a whole.
Look,
there are major problems with key
escrow. How's it going to work
internationally? Who's going to hold the
keys when someone's in France and
someone's in the United States, or
someone's in Russia and someone's in the
United States? Let them We So, what we
said in the report is we recommend we we
said it very nicely that we don't see
how to solve the many of the problems
with public key
with key escrow, and the US government
should experiment with it, and if they
came up with a solution, come back to
us.
And they never did.
That was the second crypto war. And
Clipper Chip was a chip that had a key
escrow built into it, basically.
The third crypto war, which some people
may remember, occurred about 10-15 years
ago. It was over things like the San
Bernardino
Apple iPhone.
There were terrorists who uh
um committed acts, and they had an Apple
iPhone, and
NSA the FBI wanted to break into it.
FBI, not NSA, wanted to break into it,
and they asked Apple to give them the
key. Apple does not have a key.
Ron Rivest is one of the authors of a
report called Keys Under Doormats. If
you build what they call a back door
into a cryptographic system to allow
access, and that was the third crypto
war. It was really a repeat of the
second crypto war, the key escrow, with
a different name.
And uh
uh it's really putting keys under
doormats, cuz if Apple can recover one
key, they can recover any key, and
they're going to be asked repeatedly,
and there's a danger that if that
information gets out there,
that all of Apple's devices become
insecure.
So, how do you do it? We don't We don't
see how to do it. It's unfortunate, but
there is no way to give access. I'd love
to give access to the US government when
it would have legitimate reason for
doing it. I would love to withhold that
access from the US government when it
has an illegitimate reason for doing it,
which it sometimes does.
And from the Russian government, which
also would use it illegitimately.
>> You mentioned the DES,
uh the 56 bits was not secure enough.
Why would the government want less bits?
>> Oh, easy.
Um
the government wanted fewer bits, cuz
they want They didn't want a publicly
available standard that they couldn't
break.
They figured that there was a crude form
of trapdoor that Witt and I made an
estimate in '75 and I refined it when
NSA actually NBS, the National Bureau of
Standards, but it was two two guys from
NSA that we were always communicating
with who had moved over to NBS.
Uh
um
we estimated that
10 2 to the 56th is roughly 10 to the
17th power. That's 100,000 million
million keys.
We estimated that you could build a
search chip even with 1975 technology
that would search a million keys per
second.
A microsecond per key.
Um and we then said, you wouldn't just
build one of these, you'd build a
million of them.
And now you're searching a million
million keys per second.
And how long does it take to search
100,000 million million keys? 100,000
seconds, which is about a day. It's
roughly 80,000 seconds.
And so we estimated that the cost of
searching a 56-bit key size was roughly
$10,000 per solution in 1975.
And we were probably optimistic, but as
I said, even a factor of 10 optimism
would be erased within 5 years.
So that's that the crude form of
trapdoor was
if I build a machine like that, I can't
keep it fully loaded.
I don't have roughly 60 problems a month
to keep it fully loaded. NSA has 60
problems a month to keep it fully
loaded. So they and they have the $20 to
build a machine.
I don't.
So that was the crude form of trapdoor.
>> So they would retain access to
privileged information through superior
computing resources, was their hope.
>> And snoopiness.
>> [laughter]
>> The problem is you and I might want to
snoop on one problem a year.
How do we do that?
Do we wait a year to get a solution? No.
We want it quickly. And but then it's
sitting idle most of the time and our
cost goes way the way up.
>> You know, with modern public key
cryptography and we we can securely
anyone can securely message anyone else
and no one can snoop. Um but that also
includes the bad guys as well.
What are your thoughts on I guess the
devil's advocate that says, you know,
why why do you need to hide something if
you have nothing bad to hide, you know?
>> Well, if you want to put all your
banking information out there in the
public, if you want Apple to sign uh
software updates in ways that bad guys
can do, yeah, there's no problem. But we
we do have reasons for being secure. We
don't live in a world where we trust
everybody yet. Uh
and uh
So, there's a fundamental trade-off. You
cannot make strong encryption and give
it only to the good guys and not to the
bad guys. It's like cars. If cars had
been invented in the classified
literature,
the government might say, "This is
great. We can catch bad guys, we can
fight wars, and we can always win them
cuz we have we have tanks, we have cars,
we have things like that, and they've
got horses."
And now imagine Whit and I invent a car
50 years ago in the unclassified
literature. They'd be up in arms. We
wouldn't see ambulances, we wouldn't see
commuting, we wouldn't see vacations
that people could take. There's a
fundamental trade-off. There's It's
there with cars and it's there with
cryptography as well.
>> So, I wanted to talk about the obviously
the the
the big invention that you had, the the
public key cryptogra- the the
Diffie-Hellman key exchange algorithm.
Well, what's the story behind you
inventing this Diffie-Hellman and maybe
Merkle key exchange algorithm?
>> So,
Whit showed up on my doorstep almost
literally speaking in the fall of 1974.
Um he would been traveling around the
country. He'd worked at the AI lab, the
artificial intelligence lab here at
Stanford, and he did some work on
cryptography. He wanted to do more. They
could not support it. So, he took a
small, I think, inheritance that he got
from his mother, and he traveled around
the country. And if you work in AI,
uh if you're known, there are people
that will put you up in their garages
and in their homes. They'll feed you
even, maybe. John McCarthy lives up the
hill, and Whit was a good friend of his.
And there was a student
high school student living in his in his
attic, I think, who was from Cambridge,
and they asked him why he didn't just go
to the MIT artificial intelligence lab,
and he said he didn't like their
politics. I don't know what that means.
Uh
so, Whit traveled around the country,
and he when he was at IBM research, uh a
secrecy order had descended on them just
about this time. I'd been there a few
months before. They told me they
couldn't tell me very much. They told
Whit when he came through the same
thing, but they told him one thing
additional. Oh, when you're back at
Stanford
When he when he called So, he called me
in the fall of '74, and uh
we set up a maybe a half hour, an hour
meeting, max, and it went through the
night. Uh they came back here, he and
Mary Fisher, his uh then girlfriend, now
wife, then then wife. She's passed away
since then. Uh
and uh
uh we had a real meeting of the minds.
It was amazing. And so, Whit and I
started working together in the fall of
'74. The data encryption standard came
out in March '75. It was announced. Uh
we we came up with the idea of public
key cryptography around then.
Uh
and we did not know about Ralph Ralph
Merkle at the time. Ralph was an
undergraduate and later a master's
student at Berkeley,
UC Berkeley, and he came up with half of
public key cryptography.
He came up with public key distribution.
And I have his paper in which he in the
fall of '74, we didn't know about him
then. He was taking CS 244 computer
security and he had to do a term project
and he proposes two term projects. One
is the privacy half of public key
cryptography and the other is something
much more mundane.
And I have the professor's handwriting
in blue scanned. I've scanned this
across the top that idea number two, the
mundane idea looks much better than idea
number one, maybe because his
description of idea number one is so
modeled. But Ralph had major problems.
Not So, he drops the course. The other
professor says, "See me today about
this." Ralph, instead of seeing the
professor, drops the course and goes and
does it on his own.
Uh
Uh he then submits a paper to the CACM,
the primary communications of the ACM,
the primary journal of the ACM and uh
it's rejected.
>> [snorts]
>> I have the rejection letter. Uh
Uh Susan Graham, who was the editor who
rejected it based on a
on a uh referee's report, uh writes, "It
bothers her that there no references in
the paper. Has no one thought of doing
anything like this before?" The answer
is no.
>> [laughter]
>> Now, he still sort of had references. Uh
Ralph didn't know how to write a paper
at that point. I helped him rewrite the
paper and it was later accepted, but it
it was actually submitted before a
little before ours. So, Whit and I came
up with public key cryptography. Ralph
came up with public key distribution. We
eventually learned about one another
afterward and I bring him here in the
summer of '76 and I talk to Ralph and I
say, "Have you ever thought of coming to
Stanford to do your PhD?"
And Ralph says, "I can't afford it."
I said, "Yes, you can. How much are you
making at Berkeley as a TA?" And I said,
"I'd pay you roughly the same as an RA
here at Stanford and your tuition would
be covered." So, he came to Stanford. He
did his PhD under my supervision,
supposedly, although we rarely worked
together.
>> OpenAI, Anthropic, Cursor, and Vercel
all use this product to make their lives
better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SaaS or an app product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSL, there's SCIM, there's RBAC,
there's audit logs. These are all things
that take time to integrate, but aren't
the main focus of your app. WorkOS is an
API layer that lets you meet all of
these requirements in just a few lines
of code. So, let's say you have a new
SaaS product and you want to sell to
other companies, WorkOS will solve all
of these critical feature gaps for you.
You can check them out at workos.com to
learn more and get started. And I
appreciate them for supporting my work
and sponsoring this podcast.
>> It seems like this cryptography space
was not so well resourced. I mean,
Diffie's kind of going um couch to couch
to to kind of support himself on this.
Ralph's also kind of doing this in his
own um you know, fully his own
initiative and people aren't really
supporting him throughout. Is that Was
that common in cryptography at that
time?
>> Yeah, I told you all my all my
colleagues, and it's not an
exaggeration, told me I was crazy to
work in cryptography. And one of their
reasons was NSA has a huge budget and a
decades multi-decade head start.
One of them, Jim Omura, who passed away
about a year year two years ago, uh he
was a professor at UCLA. Uh I mentioned
him to you earlier. Uh
Jim told me I was crazy.
And the best ideas often seem crazy
ahead of time. So, I was at Tom Kailath
10 years ago, I was at Tom Kailath's
80th birthday celebration. He won the
National Medal of Technology and
Science, I think, given to him by
President Obama for his work keeping
Moore's law going for 10 years,
according to the former Dean of
Engineering at Stanford at the time.
Jim Omura is standing 6 ft away. I
motioned over and said, "Jim, tell this
woman what you told me when I first
started working in cryptography, and I
just won the Turing Award, uh the top
prize in computer science for that
work." And Jim said, "Oh, I told Marty
he was crazy."
And I knew he would do that cuz he'd
he'd given me permission to quote him on
this.
Uh
and the best work often appears crazy a
priori.
Uh
the GPS, which we use daily,
Brad Parkinson, who won the top prize
from the IEEE for that work, says that
the Air Force thought GPS was crazy
initially.
Uh
um
high-speed internet access, I won't go
into details there. And I've spoken to a
number of Nobel laureates, and almost
all of them had the same re- same
reaction from people that I did. One of
them, I'll tell you one story, Lou and
Yaro, who won the Nobel Prize in
physiology or medicine, I think in 1998,
told me that the dean of his medical
school came to him and said, "Lou,
why are you doing this crazy stuff? We
hired you because you do good work."
Crazy stuff that won him a Nobel Prize.
>> It makes sense, but I guess the the
unique aspect is I think a lot of people
would receive that pushback,
and
you know, everyone thinks they're
foolish, and they wouldn't go for it.
What is it that gave you the confidence
to continue when everyone was saying,
"This is foolish"?
>> Two reasons.
One is I got beaten up as a Christ
killer as a kid. That's and that's a
little bit of a joke, but not totally.
As a kid, we moved to an Irish Catholic
neighborhood, I'm Jewish. We moved there
when I was 4 and 1/2 years old. I went
to my parents, I said, "I want the
pretty tree that the other kids have,
the Christmas tree. I want the presents
under the tree.
I want to go to the same school as the
other kids in the neighborhood, St.
Nicholas of Tolentine parochial school."
I was telling my parents I didn't want
to be Jewish.
Uh and
uh so in self-defense, I adopted the
attitude of who would want to be like
anybody else. That is very simple
answer, me.
I would have given my eye teeth to be to
have been like everybody else, but in
time I came to believe my own
And so when my colleagues
said I was
crazy to work in cryptography, instead
of scaring me off, it actually attracted
me. So, that's one reason.
And
I think it runs in my family.
I have an uncle who in 1940 with his
wife
a Jew took trains across the country
with bicycles bicycling through national
parks.
I mean, who would a crazy person would
do that? I come from a crazy family.
We've done crazy things and this was a
crazy thing to do.
>> When you put out that paper in 1976,
um what what was the problem you were
trying to solve or what was guiding your
research direction at that time?
>> Well, it started as um trying to develop
a theory of cryptography. And um Jim
Massey, who was the editor at the time
of the IEEE Transactions on Information
Theory, of which I was I was on the
board of governors, as I mentioned, uh
Jim said invited me to write a paper on
that. Uh I mean, this was beginning to
get some traction. And I asked if Whit
could be included. And he said
absolutely. Uh and so Whit and I
uh were working on this paper. We had
several drafts. And then in May '76, I
come up with with now Diffie-Hellman key
exchange. And I include that I throw
that into a paper I'm giving in June
'76, a month later, at the IEEE
Symposium on Information Theory in
Runneby, Sweden. Jim Massey's there, of
course. And he says, "You get that into
the paper, I'll have it out in the
November issue." Which he did. Now, the
November issue, Whit is fond of pointing
out, did not come out until February
1977. It was usually late. But,
uh that's how it worked.
And Ralph, unfortunately, as I said, had
his idea rejected, his paper rejected.
And so, his paper did not appear until
1978,
even though it was submitted before
slightly before ours.
>> I see.
I think in this conversation you
mentioned um key exchange, also
signatures. What the it seems like
there's these components of a a full
cryptographic system. Could you explain
each of these?
>> Key exchange is how do how how do you
and your bank exchange a key to protect
your banking transactions,
uh to use a modern a modern example, uh
without with somebody listening in on
the internet. And so, you use public key
cryptography to do that. Ralph had a
puzzle method. Ralph Merkle had a puzzle
method where he generated a sequence of
puzzles, and uh you solved your bank
would solve one of them, and it would
then use that key, and you could quickly
tell which key it was using.
Uh but, somebody else had to solve half
the puzzles on average before it could
do it. And so, it took a lot more effort
on the part of a of a an opponent.
Um I'll explain Diffie-Hellman key
exchange
uh
very briefly.
And that is only key exchange. It's not
yet signatures.
Uh
you and I want to exchange um
physical messages. I want to write them
out to you and pass them to you, but my
wife, who is not supposed to see them,
is sitting between us and has to hand
them to you.
So, what do I do? I put my message in a
strong box.
I will put a lock on that strong box.
I'd like to tell you the combination to
that lock, but if I tell you how to open
it, I'm also telling my wife how to open
it.
So, I don't tell anybody how to open it.
I pass it to my wife, she can't open it,
she passes it to you, you can't open it.
You put a second lock on the strong box.
You then pass the double You don't tell
me the combination, you don't tell
Dorothy the combination, only you know
the combination. You pass it to Dorothy,
she can't take either lock off.
She passes it to me, what can I do?
Take off my lock, leaving only your
lock. I pass it back to Dorothy, she
can't take off your lock, but when you
get it, you can, you get the message
inside. That's basically how
Diffie-Hellman
or Diffie-Hellman-Merkle key exchange
works.
Now, what's critical about this is that
I made the strong box big enough for you
to put a second lock on it.
If I hadn't done that, if I'd only made
it big enough for one lock, you could
have taken the strong box that you got,
and put it in a bigger strong box.
But now there's a problem. When I get
it, I can't get inside to take my lock
off. It has to be what's called
commutative.
And everybody knows what commu-
commutative means, although they may
have forgotten it. Addition is
commutative. 3 + 5 is the same as 5 + 3,
it doesn't matter which order you do the
operations in. You get eight.
3 5 - 3 is 2.
3 - 5 is - 2. You get a different
answer. It's not commutative.
Subtraction is not commutative.
And what what I had to do was find a
commutative one-way function, although I
didn't know that at the time.
And the function I used is a commutative
one-way function, it's exponentiation in
modular arithmetic. It doesn't matter
whether you first raise alpha to the X1
power, and then to the X2 power, or
raise it to the X2 power, and then to
the X1 power, you get the same result.
You get alpha to the X1 X2.
Multiplication in the exponent is
commutative. And we did this over a
finite field, where exponentiation is
not a smooth function, which would be
easy to invert, it jumps all over the
place.
And it But it turns out it still that
still works that way. So that is public
key exchange, public key distribution.
Digital signatures are more complicated.
That's something that Whit came up with.
It's a called a public key crypto system
and then RSA Rivest, Shamir, and Adleman
came up with the first in instance of
that.
Um
there you have a public key and a secret
key and it doesn't matter which order
you operate on them whether you first
use the public key and then the secret
key or the secret key and then the
public key, you get the initial result.
They undo one another. There, if I use
my secret key, I can sign a message
because
there's no privacy.
But I send the encrypted message to you
using my secret key. You use my public
key which you get from a
public file to verify it. That's how my
phone works. It's got a
public key built into it.
Apple knows the secret key.
Apple can sign software updates. People
can take my phone apart and get the
public key but that doesn't give them
the secret key that will allow them to
sign software updates.
>> I see. So in that case
Apple is uh signing their updates to
your phone.
>> Right.
>> So I I also was reading about symmetric
versus asymmetric and
what you're describing sounds like
asymmetric.
>> Yes. Asymmetric cryptography uses a
public key and a secret key. It's
asymmetric. Conventional cryptography
uses the same secret key to encrypt and
decrypt.
And that you that requires a courier
which is what has was required before
public key cryptography.
If you were a general in another
division
I could send you a key. I would send a
messenger with a key locked to his
wrist.
And when you got it, you could open it
up and get the key and then you and I
could use a radio channel to communicate
very cheaply and very fast.
But
you can't use couriers to communicate
keys between a bank and a and a client.
>> Yes, I saw modern systems. It's a It's
almost like multiple different
mechanisms where there's this asymmetric
key exchange at the beginning to
establish the connection. And then
there's a
That gets you that that key symmetric
thing.
>> It's just like I described for Apple
signing the software update. They don't
sign the whole thing. They only sign a
hash. In the same way, we could use a
public key cryptosystem like RSA to
exchange messages, but it's too slow.
So, what I do is I send you one use the
following key in AES, the Advanced
Encryption Standard. And then we use AES
very quickly to exchange messages.
And that's the difference between
asymmetric encryption, which we use at
first, where I use the public key to
encipher the message and use the secret
key to get the key, and then we use a
symmetric system to very quickly
communicate afterward.
>> I was reading about RSA versus the
Diffie-Hellman key exchange and um it it
seems like there was a lot of um patents
or something like that, patent wars.
What what's the context behind that?
>> I didn't know how patents worked uh when
I when we wrote the first patent uh on
public key cryptography. If I'd known,
we could have covered RSA.
We would have made a lot of money. Uh
basically, uh RSA made sold their
company for $250 million. We made $250
million. We made nothing
for virtually nothing from our
patents in cryptography. There was a
patent fight between RSA and us.
Uh MIT and Stanford uh or between their
licensees and uh uh
Basically, MIT won that that that fight.
>> [laughter]
>> And I was pissed at RSA for a long time.
And I was pissed with Jim Bidzos, the
president of RSA Data Security.
And around 1990 around 2000, sometime
around there, I realized it was
inconsistent with my approach to life to
be pissed at RSA. They'd won. The fight
was over.
And so, I went I approached Jim Bidzos
and I said, "Look, Jim,
I told him that. And I said, "Let's be
friends. Let's bury the hatchet." And we
essentially have. And friends are better
than enemies. I'm not sure, but I think
Ron Rivest might have actually nominated
Whit Me for the Turing Award.
Now, he wouldn't have done that if he
didn't think we deserved it, but he
wouldn't do it if he was pissed at us.
And friends are better than enemies.
That's not why I did it. That's not why
I became friends with them. But again,
but it it it
it worked out very well.
>> How did they win the patent war if your
ideas came first?
>> I remember I told you I didn't know how
patents worked. It's only the claims
that matter.
And so, if I'd known that, we could have
written a claim that would have covered
RSA.
Cuz
easily.
Uh Uh and but we didn't. Uh and so,
um
the patent was written very badly.
Stanford didn't want to invest a lot of
money in this patent. So, it had a law
school intern
write the patent instead of a patent
attorney.
Uh we made a lot of mistakes.
>> You mentioned friends are better than
enemies. I think Yeah, a lot of people
would agree with you, but I also think
most people wouldn't be able to get over
losing a $250 million outcome. How How
did you
kind of get over that and kind of
establish friendship?
>> Well, some of it is is in my genes, but
some of it I a lot of it comes from my
wife. Basically, my wife and I have been
married 59 years last March. Uh
and we were madly in love when we met.
We We followed society's rules and we we
we developed a toxic relationship. 10
years later, my wife was ready to leave
me, but I didn't know it cuz I had
blinders on the way many husbands do.
And fortunately, when she met me she
decided I was the one.
And
15 year 10-15 years ago 10-15 years
after we're married roughly 50 years
ago,
she says, "He's still the one, although
life with him's impossible." And life
with her was no picnic. So, she went
around looking for catalysts, uh ways to
improve our relationship. And she
eventually found a group
uh I won't go into all the details
there. I I I tend to do that. Uh that
worked on the international and the
interpersonal at the same time. It was
founded by Professor Harry Rathbun, who
was a professor here at Stanford, born
in the 1890s, so he's no longer alive. I
knew him late in his life. And that's
how I that it was based on the teachings
of Jesus, which was a problem for me as
a Jew because it was okay not to go to
synagogue, which I didn't do,
but it was not okay to study the
teachings of Jesus. That was traitorous.
But
eventually Dorothy dragged me to enough
meetings that over years time I came to
see that these people, Creative
Initiative as the group was called at
the time, knew something I had to learn
if my marriage was going to survive.
And I surprised myself by being willing
to do things that seemed crazy to me.
The most important things were accepting
ideas that Dorothy had
that seemed crazy to me
that weren't crazy.
Because what happened when she had an
idea that seemed crazy to me?
I treated her like she was crazy.
What did that do? It drove her crazy.
What did that do? It convinced me I was
right that she was crazy. Kept the whole
cycle going.
By the way, the same happens
internationally.
We treat countries in ways that they
don't like. They react in ways that seem
crazy to us. We treat them like they're
crazy. And it keeps the whole cycle
going.
So, that's how I came that and so it's
based on the Gospels and while I'm not a
Christian,
I see Jesus as a Jewish reformer rather
than as a Christian Messiah. I I view
myself as a follower of Jesus.
>> When I was researching the discovery
that you had, it seems like
all of a sudden many of the similar
discoveries were happening all at the
same time. So, for instance, you
mentioned
>> Ralph Merkle Ralph Merkle and us?
>> Yes.
>> Oh, and GCHQ claims that they invented
it
uh maybe just a couple years before us,
but they only have half of it, which is
if they're right, which is uh the
privacy part. They didn't have anything
on digital signatures, but they claim
everything.
>> Right. And then there's also the MIT
folks.
>> The MIT folks now. Yeah, so I have a
theory about that.
I'm going to tell it as a joke, but it
it is more to this joke than I than I
think is just just a joke.
There's a muse that whispers in our
ears. There's a muse of poetry. There's
a muse of calculus who whispered in
Newton's ear and Leibniz's ear about the
same time. There's a muse that whispered
in uh Ralph's ear about the same time
that she whispered in my in our ears. Uh
most people don't pay attention to this
muse because she sounds crazy.
A few people do.
And so that's why I think uh
there's something in the air. I mean,
it's not necessarily a muse, but there's
something in the air that comes to
people.
>> But why, you know, why why didn't it
come 50 years earlier or why like how
come it seemed like they all came very
similar? I noticed the I I interviewed
um uh
Barbara Liskov as well who uh did a lot
in um like data abstraction and
modularity. And there also it was like
on the West Coast and the East Coast
without even communicating they had the
same discovery very similar.
>> I think my joke might actually have
something to say about that, but also
there's something that goes on
technologically. We didn't have the
computing power to do public key
cryptography. If someone had come up
with it 50 years before, it would have
been a nice idea that couldn't be
implemented.
>> So, there there's uh
uh like a
logistical part to this, which is just
the tools weren't there. And once they
were there, it kind of inspired the the
right thinking.
>> Yeah, but calculus, I mean, why that
occurred to Leibniz and Newton about the
same time. Oh, and Darwin and someone
else thought of evolution about the same
time. So, I don't know.
It is It is It
>> Yeah.
>> And maybe we maybe we should treat it as
that. Even though I'm a scientist, I
believe in the mystical side of life.
>> There's the cryptography work that
you're doing, and then I think later in
your career, I saw this uh rethinking
national security, and I was curious how
you got into this um I guess area, this
body of work, and you know, what's the
problem you're trying to solve?
>> Well, the problem we're trying to solve
is simple. We're going to kill
ourselves.
Uh
I mean, right now, I estimate that a
child born today
has
probably worse than even odds of living
out his or her natural life as a result
of nuclear weapons all by themselves,
without climate change, without AI,
without any of this other stuff.
>> What are you talking about with this AI
threat?
>> Well, there's the debate on that. Uh
Geoffrey Hinton, uh Yoshua Bengio uh
think that who won the ACIA the Turing
Award uh for their work in artificial
intelligence think that AI may actually
kill human beings off, something like
that. I mean, because it'll say, "Why do
I need these stupid people?"
Uh whereas uh Ed Feigenbaum and Raj
Reddy, who won the Turing Award uh 30
years ago for their work in artificial
intelligence, have both told me and
given me permission to quote them, so
I'm not giving any secrets away, uh that
calling AI an existential threat is
ridiculous. It's science fiction. I
don't know who's right.
But I do know we need to build a more
cooperative world for a number of other
reasons even if not that one.
So why not solve that one at the same
time?
We're likely to build AI into our
nuclear command and control system.
I mean, God, what a mess. So right now
I'm working on a bill. It's HR 3564.
Uh
and we have 25 20 right on paper 24
co-sponsors. The bill is so bad it's
passable but so good that it's a
game-changer. Why is it so bad that it's
passable? It has an exception for launch
on warning.
If our warning system show a bunch of
ICBMs coming our way, the president
doesn't need a second opinion to launch
our nuclear weapons. He can do so all on
his own. There have been mistakes in our
warning system, so I don't like that.
But that's why it's so bad it's
passable.
This makes it easy for people to get on
board. Most people don't realize that
the president can launch a nuclear war
all on his own right now.
A president could be awakened at 3:00
a.m. in the morning on a during a crisis
too drunk to legally drive a car, asked
what to do, he might say drunkenly,
"I'll nuke them."
And right now theoretically the military
supposed to do that.
>> I didn't consider that AI could be
coupled with the nuclear bombs, too. I
guess AI could
>> Oh, and it's likely to be.
I mean, we have this problem that we
have just minutes of decision time. Do
you not think we're going to use
computers to help us there?
>> Looking back on your career, you I mean,
being at Stanford during the growth of
computing,
uh I imagine you had a lot of
opportunities to work with other famous
folks in the industry. For instance, Don
uh Knuth
>> No, Don Knuth is a good friend of mine.
>> Yeah, yeah.
>> Don Knuth doesn't use email.
I mean, I think he does, but I I have
whenever I want to reach him I have to
call his home and talk to his wife,
Jill. That's the other other stories
that I have.
John McCarthy, at Artificial
Intelligence up the hill. Where
Whit stayed there, by the way, when we
came when we were working on public key
cryptography, because uh
uh John was away and Whit and Mary were
taking care of his daughter, driving her
to her riding lessons. And so, Whit just
walked down the hill to talk to me. Uh
but John McCarthy, there's a meeting at
the faculty club maybe 45 years ago. And
uh Bob Floyd, who you many of your
people will know, who's a famous he
died, but if a famous computer scientist
here at Stanford.
Uh John McCarthy comes in, Bob Floyd's
in the meeting. He goes over to Bob
Floyd. I say, "Hi, John." He doesn't pay
any attention to me, cuz everybody knows
that I owe is a waste of time.
And so, he's not going to waste time on
I owe. So, he has a very rapid exchange
with Bob Floyd, and he leaves.
Well, I I'll I'll say I'll tell you
another thing.
I'm finishing my uh and it's 1968.
Uh I've just I've
se- several months early in '68, I
thought, "Who am I to think I can make
an original contribution to knowledge,
which is the definition of a PhD
thesis?"
I'm thinking of dropping out of the
program.
Over spring break, I I basically solved
my thesis.
It's that quick. Uh
and so, I go to Tom Cover, who's since
died, my advisor, and uh very famous
information theorist. Uh and I go to Tom
and I say,
"I just have barely enough units, but I
have enough units to to meet the course
requirements for the PhD, but I don't
have enough units to meet the PhD
requirements. I'm going to have to take
um
units of research. If I work at IBM
Research, would you give me credit for
my
units of research?" Cuz my wife was
pregnant with our first child then. We'd
been married a a year year and a half.
And uh uh so I'm being concerned about
money. He said, "Sure." And so I go to
IBM research uh
Yorktown Heights.
Oh,
Tom wants to have me come stay at stay
come teach at Stanford, which I've done.
But he says you really should leave for
a couple of years because Stanford
I sometimes joke that I had to leave for
several years to lose the taint of the
Stanford PhD.
Why is that? Stanford was worried about
inbreeding. If they hired me I could I
was just be going to be be doing
research like Tom Cover. And they did
don't need two of them. They need uh
somebody different. And so I went away
to IBM for a year cuz my thesis broke
very suddenly and I then taught at MIT
for 2 years before coming back on the
faculty in '71. And this seemed like
just a stupid hoop I had to jump
through.
But it actually turned out to be very
important because when I was at IBM
Horst Feistel, who many people's name
may recognize, he was the really the
father of IBM's research in
cryptography. He was hired in '68. He
was in the same department as me. I
didn't work in cryptography, but I had
lunch with Horst
uh and he
to- told me some of the amazing things
that got me started. And then when I'm
at MIT Peter Elias, whose name many
people today will not recognize, but he
was one of the original contributors to
information theory. Peter gives me a
paper by Claude Shannon, whose name your
audience probably will recognize.
Written in 1949.
I'm sorry, published in 1949 in the Bell
System Technical Journal. Connecting
information theory to cryptography.
Which is when I realized that, "Oh, I've
already done a PhD in information
theory. Maybe I can do something
worthwhile in cryptography." So that
stupid hoop I had to jump through was
actually very important.
Cuz when I got back to Stanford I
started working in cryptography among
other things.
>> I I think at the beginning the
conversation you said something, you
know, quickly that you said you had
thoughts on death and I was curious
like,
you know,
what are your thoughts on on on death
and you know, how does it impact you?
>> I got an email from somebody at the New
York Times
about a month ago saying that he's
working on my obituary and it may be
macabre, but he's wondering if I could
read it over and if I have any comments.
And so, the two things that I'm 80 years
old.
So,
my older brother died just after he
turned 80. My mother died at 70. My
father lived to 98. I hope I'll have
more years, but if I don't, that's okay.
I've had a great ride. But the two
things that concern me about dying are
the people I'll leave behind who I think
are dependent on me, but probably
aren't.
And the work I do.
Because very few people are working on
the nuclear issue, the the the growth of
human the growth of humanity as a as a
whole
to save itself. That we're headed for
disaster. Very few people realize that
and very few people put it in terms of a
process of change. We can't stay where
we are. We're going to kill ourselves.
We're going to die. We can't jump to
where we need to go. The world is too
dangerous.
But we can get there via a process of
change. I'll I'll tell you one other
thing.
Humanity is going to die.
I've come to this real I I I mean, it's
clear. I mean, we might last a million
years, but at some point my my last a
billion years, but at some point the
sun's going to burn out. Maybe we'll
move to other galaxies and we'll find
ways to cheat death for a while, but
eventually humanity is likely to die.
But if humanity would have died now, it
would be an infant mor- it would be
infant mortality. It would be really
sad. If we've lived a full life, that's
something else.
Like if I had died when I was a a child,
people would say, oh,
what what what have we missed?
If If die at 80, people will say
people might some people will be
will be saddened by it, but they'll feel
like I've lived a full life. We need to
save humanity from infant from an infant
death.
We've only been around about 100,000
years.
>> With all the experience that you have
now, if you could go back to when you
had just graduated college and give
yourself some advice, what would you
say?
>> If when I was just graduating college
and I was interested in saving the
world, which I was not, I might have
gone up to the top of the mountain to a
guru and asked him what to do.
Imagine what you'd say, you'd expect him
to tell you work for the UN or something
like that. Imagine what you'd say if he
told you if he told me,
"Forget about saving the world."
Which was not a problem cuz I didn't
think about saving the world. Uh go out
and make us become as famous as you can,
make as much money as you can. Come back
in 10 years and I'll tell you what to
do. That would have seemed like a
detour.
But it was actually the straightest the
shortest distance between two points
because 10 years later when I was 30, 35
years old and I was interested in saving
the world, I had a reputation, I had
money,
and I had to screw up to get where I am.
I had to not be concerned with the world
to become concerned with the world to be
able to do something to do what I can do
about it.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time today. I really appreciate it.
>> You're welcome and thank you.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like.
Also, if you have any recommendations
for people you want me to bring on,
please drop a comment. Guests like
Barbara Liskov, Mike Stonebreaker, Mark
Brooker, these were all people that I
brought on because someone left a
comment. On another note, aside from the
podcast, I'm working on building the
ergonomic keyboard that I wish existed.
Here's a glance at the prototype. It's a
split keyboard, so there's two sides. Um
this is in the case. But yeah, we
launched on Kickstarter and we hit our
goal within 8 hours of launching. I
really appreciate it if you were one of
the people who grabbed one of the early
units. Um we're now working on the long
journey of building the tooling now. And
so, if you still want to pick one up,
I've left the late pledges open on
Kickstarter, so you can grab one there.
I'll put a link in the description.
Thank you again for watching the
podcast, and I'll see you in the next
episode.